There is an immense literature on attacking block ciphers.
有大量关于攻击分组密码的文献.
In this segment, I just want to give you a taste for
what these attacks look like.
在这一节里,我只想让你体验一下这些攻击是什么样子的.
And I hope I'll convince you that you should never
ever design your own block cipher,
同时我希望我能说服你们永远不要设计你自己的分组密码,
and just stick to the standards like Triple DES
and AES.
而是坚持使用例如3DES和AES这样的标准.
The first set of attacks that I want to talk about
我想要讨论的第一类攻击
are attacks on the
implementation of the block cipher.
是在分组密码实现中的攻击.
As an example, imagine you have a smart card that's implementing a block cipher.
例如,想像一下你有一块实现了分组密码的智能卡.
So the smart card, for example, could be used for
credit card payments. It might have a
这块智能卡可能会被用作信用卡支付.它可能会有一个
secret key inside of it to authenticate
your credit card payments as you stick the
内部密钥来鉴定信用卡的支付行为，当你把卡插入
card into a payment terminal, say. So now,
if an attacker obtains your smart card,
一个支付终端时, 现在如果一个攻击者获取了你的智能卡,
what he could do is he could actually take
the smart card to a lab, and then run the
他可能会把卡拿到实验室去运行这张卡
card, and measure very precisely how much
time the card took to do encryption and
非常精确地测量出这张卡加密和解密所用的时间
decryption. Now, if the amount of time
that the implementation took to do
现在，如果实现加密过程所用的时间
encryption depends on bits of the secret
key, then by measuring the time, the
取决于密钥的位数, 通过测量时间
attacker will learn something about your
secret key and in fact, he might be able
攻击者就可以获取关于密钥的一些信息，事实上
to completely extract your secret key. And
there are many examples of implementations
他可以完全获得你的密钥。有许多这样的例子
that simply by measuring the time very
precisely for many operations of
仅仅通过精确测量加密算法的时间
encryption algorithms, you can completely
extract the secret key. Another example is,
你就可以完全获得密钥. 另一个例子是,
rather than just measuring the time, you
can actually measure the power consumption
不是测量时间, 而是测量智能卡的运行功耗
of the card as it's operating. So,
literally, you can connect it to a device
这样，你可以将其连接到一个设备上
that will measure the current that the
card is drawing and then graph the
测量它运行时的电流，然后用曲线图非常精确地记录它们。
currents very, very precisely. Now, these
cards are not very fast, and as a result,
这些智能卡不是很快，这样的话，
you can actually measure the exact amount
of power consumed at every clock cycle as
当卡在运行时你可以测量每个时钟周期里的精确能耗
the card was executing. When you do that,
you actually get graphs of this form.
这样，你就可以得到这种类型的图
So this is an example of a smart card
operating, while it's doing the
这是一个智能卡工作时的例子
DES computation. So you can see
very clearly, here's when it was doing
当它进行DES运算时. 你可以很清楚地看到，
the initial permutation. Here's when it's
doing the final permutation. And then,
这里是它在进行初始置换，这里是它在进行最终置换
here, you can count. There are actually
sixteen hills and troughs
看这里，你可以数一下，这里有16个波峰和波谷
corresponding to the sixteen rounds. And
essentially when you zoom in on a graph
对应了16个轮。 当你像这样放大图表
like this, you can basically read the key
bits off one by one, just by looking at
你可以将密钥位逐位读出
how much power the card consumed as it was
doing the different operations. It turns out
只需要关注智能卡在进行不同操作时的功耗就可以
that, even cards that take steps to mask
this type of information, are still
实际上，就算智能卡对这些信息进行伪装，依然易受攻击
vulnerable. There's an attack called differential power analysis, where
这种攻击叫做差分功耗分析
basically, you measure the power consumed
by the card over many, many, many, runs of
当智能卡重复运行加密算法时测量卡的功耗
the encryption algorithm. And as long as
there's any even small dependence between
只要电流消耗上有很小的差异
the amount of current consumed and the
bits of the secret key, basically that
密钥各位之间的依赖性就会出现
dependence will show up after enough runs of the encryption algorithm. And as a
加密算法运行足够多的次数
result you'll be able to completely
extract the secret key. Okay, so these
这样就可以完全获得密钥
attacks were actually discovered by Paul
Kocher and his colleagues up at
这些攻击是由Paul Kocher和他的同事在密码学研究所发现的
Cryptography Research and there's actually
a fairly large industry devoted to just
有一个很大的产业来专门防御功耗攻击
defending against these power attacks. As
far as timing attacks are concerned,
如果考虑计时攻击的话
I want to mention that these are real.
They're not just about smart cards.
我想说这些都是真的。不仅仅针对智能卡
For example, you can imagine a multicore
processor where the encryption algorithm
比如，设想一个多核的处理器，其中一核运行加密算法
is running on one core and the attacker
code happens to be running on another
攻击代码运行在另一个核
core. Now these cores actually share the
same cache. And as a result, an attacker
这些代码实际上使用的是同一缓存
can actually measure or can actually look
at the exact cache misses that the
这样的话攻击者可以测量或者直接观测加密算法中的缓存缺失
encryption algorithm incurred. It turns
out that by looking at cache misses, you
实际上，通过观测这些缓存缺失
can completely figure out the secret key
used by the algorithms. So, one core can
你可以完整地得到算法中使用的密钥
essentially extract information from the
other core, just by looking at cache misses.
所以，通过观察缓存缺失，某一核可以从另一核中提取信息
So implementing these block ciphers is actually quite subtle
所以实现分组密码是比较困难的
because you have to make sure that the
side channel attacks don't leak
因为你需要保证旁道攻击不会泄露你的密钥信息
information about your secret key. Another
type of attack that's been discussed in
另一类被很多文献讨论的攻击
the literature is what's called a fault
attack. So here, basically, if you're
我们称之为错误攻击.
attacking a smart card, you can actually
cause the smart card to malfunction,
当你攻击一个智能卡时，实际上会造成智能卡工作异常
perhaps by overclocking it, perhaps by
warming it up. Essentially, you can cause
可能是时钟频率过高，可能是芯片过热
the processor to, malfunction, and output
erroneous data. It turns out that, if,
你会导致处理器工作异常并输出错误的数据
during encryption, there are errors in the
last round of the encryption process, the
在加密过程中，如果最后一轮出现错误
resulting ciphertexts that are produced are
enough to actually expose the secret key K.
产生的密文足以暴露密钥K
That's quite an interesting result that
in fact if you have any errors, if you ever
这是一个有趣的结果，实际上如果有任何错误
output a wrong result, that actually could
completely compromise your secret key.
如果输出了一个错误的结果，那么可能就会暴露你的密钥
So, of course, the defense against this means
that before you output the result of your
因此，抵御这种攻击意味着你要在算法输出结果前
algorithm, you should check to make sure
that the correct result was computed.
进行检查来确保计算出正确的结果
Now of course that's nontrivial, because how do
you know that the error didn't happen
当然要做到这一点并不容易，因为你也不知道你的检查算法中有没有错误
in your checking algorithm. But there are
known ways around that. So basically you
不过还是有其他已知的方法
can actually compute something three or
four times, take the majority over all those
你可以计算三次或者四次，只要计算中不出现太多错误
results, and be assured that the output
really is correct as long as not too many
并保证输出是正确的
faults occurred inside of your computation. These are attacks on the implementation.
就取结果中的占多数的结果。这些是实现过程中的攻击
I hope these examples can assure you that not only should you not
我希望这些例子可以确保大家不仅不要
invent your own block ciphers, you should
never even implement these crypto
设计自己的分组密码，而且不要自己去实现这些密码原型
primitives yourself. Because A, you have
to make sure there are no side channel
因为首先，你需要确保实现过程中没有旁道攻击
attachments on your implementation and B,
you have to make sure that the
其次，你需要确保
implementation is secure against fault
attacks. Okay so, instead you should just
实现过程针对错误攻击是安全的
use standard libraries like the ones
available in OpenSSL and many other
所以大家应该只使用那些例如OpenSSL等可以获得的标准库
libraries out there. So don't implement
these primitives yourself, just use
所以不要自己去实现这些原型
existing libraries. All right, so now I want
to turn to kind of more sophisticated
只去使用已有的库。好的，现在我要讨论一种更为复杂针的对分组密码的攻击
attacks on block ciphers and I'll particularly
talk about how these attacks apply to DES.
我想特别讨论一下针对DES的攻击
Okay so these attacks were discovered by
Biham and Shamir back in 1989, and I'll
这些攻击由Biham和Shamir在1989年发现
particularly describe a version of the
attack discovered by Matsui in 1993.
我将特别讲述Matsui在1993年发现的攻击版本
So the goal here is basically given many,
many input-output pairs, can we actually
所以，如果实在给定很多的输入输出对情况下
recover the key better than exhaustive
search? So anything that runs better than
我们能否比穷举搜索更好地还愿密钥？
exhaustive search already counts as an
attack on the block cipher. Okay, so the
任何比穷举搜索更好的攻击都算是分组密码攻击
example I want to give you is what's called
linear cryptanalysis. And here imagine it
我想给你们的例子叫做线性密码分析
so happens that, you know, c is the
encryption of m using key k, and
试想，c是m用密钥k加密得到，
suppose it so happens that if I look at
random key and a random message, somehow
假定我随机地观察密钥和信息
there's a dependence between the message,
ciphertext, and the key bits. In
那么明文、密文和密钥位之间存在着某种联系
particular, if I XOR a subset of
the message bits, so this is just a
特别地，如果我逐位异或一组明文比特
subset of the message bits, if I XOR that with a certain subset of the ciphertext
这是一组明文比特，如果我异或一组特定的密文比特
bits. So these two the attacker
sees. The attacker has the message and the
这样两组攻击者都能看到
attacker has the ciphertext. And then you
compare that to an XOR of a subset of
攻击者同时有明文和对应的密文，然后将其与密钥的异或进行比较
the key bits. Now if the two were
completely independent which is what you'd
如果两者能如你所愿完全独立的话，
like, you definitely don't want your
message and your ciphertext to somehow
我们当然不希望明文和密文
predict your key bits, if the two are
like, completely independent, then this
能用某种方式预测密钥。如果他们完全独立
equality will hold with probability
exactly one-half. But suppose it so
那么这个等式成立的概率就严格地为1/2
happens that there's a bias and this
probability holds with probability half
但是设想有一点不均匀导致这个等式的概率
plus epsilon for some small epsilon. It so
happens that, in fact, for DES, there is
是1/2加上某个小ε 。事实上，对于DES有这样的关系
such a relation. The relation holds
specifically because of a bug in the design
这个关系之所以成立是因为第五个S盒子的设计有一个BUG
of the fifth S-box. It turns out the fifth
S-box happens to be too close to a linear
事实上第五个S盒子太过于接近线性函数了
function. And that linear function,
basically, as it propagates through the
那个线性函数传遍了整个DES的计算过程
entire DES circuit, generates a relation
of this type. You notice, this is
产生了这样的一个关系
basically a linear relation that's being
computed here. So, this small tiny, tiny
注意这里计算的是一个线性关系
linearity in the fifth S-box generates
this relation over the entire circuit,
因此第五个S盒子的微弱线性关系会对整个算法产生这样的关系
where the epsilon is tiny. Epsilon is one
over 2^21, and I wrote down what
这里的ε是很小的，约为2的21次方分之一
that is. So the bias is really, really,
really small. But nevertheless, there is a
这个偏量真的真的很小
bias using these particular subsets of bits. Now, I'm not going to show you how to
但是在使用这些特殊的比特时也会有偏量
derive this relation, or I'm not going to show you even what it is. I'll just tell you
现在我不打算推导这个关系，也不告诉大家这是什么意思
how to use a relation like this once you find it. Okay. So here's our relation
我只告诉你们当你找到它的时候如何使用这个关系
that we have. And the question is how to
use it. So with a little bit of statistics
这里我们只关心如何使用它。用一点统计的知识
you can actually use an equation like this
to determine some of the key bits. And
你就可以使用这样的一个等式来决定某些比特
here's you do it. Suppose you were given one over epsilon squared message-ciphertext pairs.
这么做：假设给定了1/ε的平方个明文-密文对
And these have to be
independently random messages and the
这些必须是互相独立的随机明文和对应的密文
corresponding ciphertexts. What you would
do is you would use the formula above. In
应用上面的公式
fact you would use the left-hand side of
the formula above to compute this relation
事实上你可以使用公式左边来计算
between the message and ciphertext for
all the pairs you were given. Now what do
你所有的明文密文对之间的关系
you know? You know that for half plus
epsilon of these values, you know that
现在，对于这些值的一半加上ε的值
these things will be equal to an
XOR of the key bits. So if you
这些值等于密钥各个位的异或
take majority over all the values you've
computed, it turns out it's not so
取计算结果中的大多数
difficult to see that in fact you'll get
the correct prediction for the XOR of the
不难看出你得到了对密钥所有位异或的正确预测
key bits with a probability of 97.7%. In
other words, if this relation happens to
其正确概率为97.7%。换句话说，如果这个关系在多于一半的时间里是正确的
be correct more than half the time, then
the majority will be right. And because
那么大多数的结果都将是正确的
there's a bias, there's an epsilon bias, the probability that you will be correct
因为有偏量ε，概率将会超过一半，事实上是99.7%
more than half the time is, in fact,
97.7%. In which case, the majority, in
实际上，大部分情况下我们是正确的
fact, will give you the correct XOR of the
key bits. Okay? So this is kinda cool.
这里的大多数结果，会给你正确的密钥所有位的异或，是不是很酷？
Within one over epsilon squared time, you
can figure out an XOR of a bunch of key
在1/ε平方的次数内，你就可以解出密钥所有位的异或 。
bits. So now, let's apply this to DES.
So, for DES, we have epsilon, which is one
现在，我们把它应用到DES。DES的ε等于0.5的21次方
over 2^21. Which means that if you give me
2^42 input-output pairs, I can
意味着如果给定2的42次方个输入输出对时
figure out an XOR of the key bits. And now,
it turns out, I'm not gonna exactly show
我可以接触密钥所有位的异或值。事实上我可以告诉大家
you how, roughly speaking, using this
method, you don't just get one key bit. In
不严格地讲，使用这个方法，你还不知道密钥中任何一位
fact, you get two key bits. You can kind
of use this relation. One's going in a
事实上，你可以取密钥中的任意两位，使用这个方法
forward direction and one's going in a
backwards direction. So that gives you two
一个向前，一个向后
XORs of bits of the secret key. Okay, so
that's two bits of information about the
这样就给你一些密钥中这两位的异或值，这样就有了密钥中两位的信息了
secret key. And then it turns out you can
get twelve more bits, because,
其实你还可以获得另外的12位
essentially, you can figure out what the
inputs are to the fifth S-box. Okay, so,
因为你可以解出第五个S盒子的输入
I'm not going to exactly show you how. But it
turns out you can get twelve more bits,
我不再详细展示了，但是是可以得到另外12位的
which is a total of fourteen bits overall.
So now, using this method, you've
这样一共就得到14位了，现在使用这个方法
recovered fourteen bits of the secret key.
And of course, it took you time 2^42.
你已经还愿了密钥中14位内容，当然这需要进行2^42次。
Okay, so then, what do you do?
Well, so the rest of it is easy. Now what
然后我们做什么呢？，剩下的部分就很简单了
you're going to do is you're going to do
exhaustive search on the remaining bits.
你只需要穷举密钥中剩余的位就可以了
Well how many remaining bits are there?
Well, there are 42 remaining bits, so
还剩下多少位呢？ 42位
the exhaustive search will take you time 2^42. So what's the total attack time?
穷举密钥花掉了 2^42 的时间。那么攻击的总用时是多少？
Well, the first step of the algorithm
to determine the fourteen bits took 2^42 time,
算法的第一步，确定14位需要2^24的时间
and the remaining brute force
search also took 2^42 time.
剩下的穷举搜索需要另一个2^42
So overall, the attack took two to the 43
time. Okay? So now, this is much better
所以攻击的总时间是2^43
than exhaustive search. Within two to the
43 time, we broke DES. But of course, this
这比穷举攻击要好很多 在2^43时间里我们破解了DES
required two to the 42 random input-output
pairs whereas exhaustive search only
不过这需要2^42个输入输出对
required three pairs. Okay, so this is a
fairly large number of input-output
而穷举搜索只需要3对。好，这里要求的明文密文对
pairs that are needed, but given such a
large number, you can actually recover the
数目还是很多的，但给定这么多
key faster than exhaustive search. Okay,
so what's the lesson in all this?
确实可以更快地还原DES密钥，通过这些我们学到了什么？
The lesson is, firstly, any tiny bit of
linearity, basically, in this— in the
第一，任何细微的线性关系
fifth S-box, which was not designed as
well as the other S-boxes, basically led
比如这里第5个S盒子不像其他S盒子设计的那么好
to an attack on the algorithm. Okay. A tiny
beat of linearity already introduced this
会导致一种攻击算法，任一细微的线性关系
linear attack. And I want to emphasize
again that this is not the sort of thing
都会引入线性攻击。再次强调一下
you would think of when you design a cipher. And so again, the conclusion here is,
这些不是在设计密码时就能够考虑到的。所以结论是
there are very subtle attacks on block
ciphers, ones which you will not be able to
对分组密码存在很复杂的攻击，仅凭自己一个人往往是无法找到的
find yourself. And so just stick to the
standards. Don't ever, ever, ever, ever
所以说要坚持使用标准，永远不要自己设计分组密码
design your block cipher. Okay, so that's
all I want to say about sophisticated
这就是关于复杂攻击所有我想说的
attacks. Now let's move on to the last
type of attack that I want to mention, which
现在我们来看最后一种攻击
I'll call quantum attacks, which are
again— these are generic attacks on
我称之为量子攻击，它对分组密码是通用的
all block ciphers. So let me explain what
I mean by this.
这里让我来解释一下
So first of all, let's look at a generic problem, a generic search problem. Suppose I have a function
首先我们来看一个普遍的问题，一个普遍的搜索问题
on some large domain X, that happens to be
two outputs, either zero or one.
假设我有一个定义在大集合X上的函数，输出有两种值 0或1
And it so happens that this function is mostly
zero. And there's, like, maybe one input
这个函数输出的大部分值都是0
where the function happens to evaluate to
one. And your goal is basically, you know,
这个函数只有一个输入，所对应的函数值为1
find me the inputs where the function
happens to be one. Maybe there's only one
目标是找出这些输入，满足函数值为1
such input. But your goal is to find it.
Well, so on a classical computer, what can
我们的目标就是要找到这个输入。那么在一台经典的计算机上
you do? The function is given to you. It's
given to you as a black box. So the best
你能做什么？函数已经给出了，作为一个黑盒
you can do is just try all possible
inputs. So this is gonna take time which
你所能做的最好是去尝试所有可能的输入
in linear in the size of the domain. Now,
it turns out there's an absolutely magical
所以需要的时间和定义域的大小是线性相关的。但现在，如果有一台
result that says that if you build a
computer that's based on quantum physics
基于量子物理的计算机的话，就会产生神奇的结果。
as opposed to classical physics, you can
solve this problem faster. So let me
而非经典物理的话，那么你可以更快地解决这个问题
explain what I mean by this. So first of
all in the 70s and 80s it was observed, I
我来解释一下。在20世纪七八十年代
think it was actually Richard Feynman who observed this initially, that said
实际上是Richard Feynman最早观察到
that it turns out to be very difficult to
simulate quantum experiments on a
在经典计算机上模拟量子实验是非常困难的
classical computer. So Feynman said, if
that's the case, maybe these quantum
所以他说，如果是这样的话
experiments are computing things that a
classical computer can't compute.
也许这些量子实验是经典计算机所无法计算的东西
So they're somehow able to compute very
quickly things that are very difficult to
所以某种意义上它们可以计算得很快
do classically. And that turned out to be
correct. And in fact, the example I want
而同样的问题经典计算机很难做到。这被证明是正确的，事实上
to show you is one of these amazing things that in fact, if you could build a
我想给大家看一个令人惊奇的的例子，如果你可以构建一个量子计算机
quantum computer that's using quantum
physics, then it's, in fact, you can solve
用于计算量子物理，那么它可以被用来
this search problem not in time X but in
time square root of X. So somehow, even
解决这个搜索问题，用不着|X|的时间，而是|X|的平方根的时间即可
though the computer doesn't know anything
about the function F, it's treating it as
即使计算机不知道任何函数F的信息
a black box, nevertheless, it's able to
find a point where the function is one, in
F被视为黑盒，但是依然可以找到一个点使其函数值为1
time square root of X. I'm not going to explain this here, but, at the end of the
在|X|的平方根的时间内，我在这里不解释其原理
class, we're gonna have an advanced topics
lecture. And if you'd like me to explain
在本课程的结尾，我们会有个高级课题的讲座
how this algorithm works, I can explain it
in that advanced topics lecture.
来解释这个算法的工作过程
It's actually quite interesting, and, in fact,
quantum computers have quite an impact on
这真的是很有趣的，事实上，量子计算机对于密码学
crypto. And again, as I said, I can
explain this in the very last lecture.
影响很大。好的 我会在最后的课程解释这些
All right. So what does this have to do with
breaking block cyphers? So far it's just a
那么，这和破解分组密码有什么关系呢？
generic search problem. Well, oh actually
I should say before I show you the
目前这仅仅是个普遍问题。对了
application, I should mention that, well,
you might be wondering, well, can someone
在谈应用前我还要说一下，大家可能想知道
build a quantum computer. And this is
still completely unknown. At this point,
能不能制造量子计算机，这个目前还完全未知
nobody really knows if we can build
large enough quantum computers to actually
没有人知道我们能否建造量子计算机
take advantage of this beautiful algorithm
due to Grover. Alright, so what does this
来利用这个Grover提供的这个优美的算法
have to do with block ciphers? Well, so
suppose I give you a message-ciphertext pair.
那么，这和分组密码有何关系？假定给你一个或几个明文密文对
Just one or just a few. We can
define a function as follows. It's a
我们可以定义如下的函数
function on K, it's a function on, the key
space. And the function will basically
这是一个定义在密钥空间K上的函数
output one if it so happens that the
encryption of m with k maps to c, and it
这个函数会输出1，如果正好满足k加密m得到c
will output zero otherwise. Now we argue
that basically this is exactly the type of
否则函数输出0。现在我们来讨论这个函数
function that's one at one point in the
key space and that's it. So by Grover's
正是在密钥空间中一点处为1
algorithm, we can actually find the secret
key in time square root of K.
那么根据Grover算法，我们可以找到密钥用|K|的平方根的时间
So what does that mean? For DES, this would
totally destroy DES. This would say
那么这以为着什么？对于DES，这足以完全摧毁DES了
that in time 2^28, you could
find a key. 2^28 is about 200 million.
因为这仅用时2^28就能找出密钥，2^28仅为2亿左右
So 200 million steps which is, you know, just takes a millisecond on a modern computer.
而现代计算机上2亿步只需要毫秒级
This would totally destroy DES. But even AES with 128-bit keys,
这足以摧毁DES了，即便是128位密钥的AES
you would be able to find the secret
key in time, roughly 2^64.
你也可以仅用2^64次的时间就找到密钥
And 2^64 is these days, considered
insecure. That's within the realm of
2^64在如今是视为不安全的
exhaustive search. And so, basically, if
somebody was able to build a quantum
它还在穷举法的范围内。所以，如果有人可以造出量子计算机
computer, we would then say that AES-128
is no longer secure. Instead, if somebody,
我们就可以说AES128不再安全
you know, if tomorrow, you open up the
newspaper, and you read an article that
如果你在明天的报纸上看到有文章说
says, you know, so-and-so built a
quantum computer, the conclusion, the
有人造出量子计算机了
consequence of all that is that you should
immediately move to block ciphers that use
那你就可以得出结论，大家必须立刻使用256位密钥的分组密码了
256 bits, because then the running time
of Grover's algorithm is 2^128,
因为256位密钥的Grover算法运行时间是2^128
which is more time than we consider
feasible, and the, basically there are
目前还是安全的
example ciphers with 256 bits, for
example, AES-256. This is one of the
也有256位的密码，比如AES256
reasons why AES was designed with 256
bits in mind. But to be honest, this is
这也是AES要设计256位密钥的原因之一
not the only reason. There are other reasons why you want it to have larger key sizes.
但其实不是唯一的原因，还有其他原因的
Okay, so this is, as I said, just a taste of the different attacks on block ciphers,
我说过，这只是带大家初尝针对分组密码的不同攻击
and I'm gonna leave it at that. If we decide on quantum for the last
到此告一段落，如果我们决定在最后一讲讨论量子算法
topic of the course, then we'll recover
that in the very last lecture.
我们还会回过来看Grover算法的